And then we'll let everyone in.
So we are now admitting everybody from
the lobby.
As a reminder,
this does usually take a minute or two.
So welcome to those who are joining.
We'll,
I'll continue to talk for a minute to
allow everybody who's in the waiting room
to actually join into the main meeting.
For those who do not know me,
I am Dominic Serlo and I'm the Center
Director for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin at the New Mexico Department
of Health.
We are recording this meeting and so we
do ask that individuals please to ensure
that you are using appropriate language
for video because we do post it on our
website.
And so people of all ages may be watching
it and we don't want to have to go in and
bleep inappropriate language for that
same reason.
That is one of two reasons why we also
keep the video off just in the in case
somebody has something happened in the
background that we would have to edit on
out and, and that it well,
it hasn't happened in our meetings.
It has happened in other meetings.
And,
but so that is one of the reasons we just
have our presenters,
the chair and some of the staff on video.
But as many of you know,
shortly after I conclude this part,
I will come off a video for most of the
meeting.
And with that we have Doctor Larry Lehman,
who is the chair of this committee,
which is the end of life care committee.
And so I will now pass it over to Larry.
So Larry, it is your meeting.
Great.
Thanks, Dominic.
Appreciate your help as always.
Welcome everybody.
Looks like we have a nice,
nice size group today, which is great.
The,
the heart of this meeting is going to be
our Daniella, our psychedelic death doula,
who's going to be really discussing,
you know, the role.
What does that involve?
But before I start,
I just want to put in a little bit of the
context in case you're joining.
This is maybe your first time.
What our group has been doing for the
last few months is really getting like a,
an idea both nationally and locally about
different roles,
really focusing on like 7 core questions.
And so sometimes the end of this,
I'm going to go look back on those 7 core
questions.
But for instance, we had Chris Caldwell,
who's the founder of End of Life PC,
talking to us.
We had Jen Clement,
who may be on the call today as well,
is a psychedelic chaplain.
Danielle's been kind enough to talk today.
James Brown,
who's a a pharmacist with interest in end
of Life here.
He's going to talk about specific issues.
The 17th.
We're still working out the exact plan,
but well, thanks.
Jennifer Johnson,
who is with the Red Willow Hospice up in
Santa Fe is going to talk about Hospice
related issues.
And then we've just firmed up that we're
going to do our first like on site
blended meeting on the 23rd of April at a
location that Danielle has been kind
enough to set up.
It's her office space at the Bioscience
Center.
So that will that will be posted and
everyone will be able to access as well,
you know, through the Zoom.
It's a nice opportunity,
I think for us to have a conversation.
Teams is very helpful.
It gets us together from around the state.
But as you know,
it tends not to be a conversation.
It's kind of individual people talking.
So we're going to try to do try to try to
do that if there's other anyone has
thoughts on other speakers to put in,
but those are kind of what we have so far.
And then we're going to be moving over
the next few months to integrating all
this and making sort of decisions and
trying to send some some guidelines for
approval.
So that's our overview.
Danielle,
thank you so much for agreeing to come
here.
It's been fun having Danielle as a
speaker because her and I have gotten to
talk to some and share perspectives.
So it's been good to get to talk to you
about this week and excited to hear hear
your presentation.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Thank you so much for having me.
Thank you to the Department of Health,
all of you for for helping with the tech
issues and everything else to to kind of
get us up and running.
Shall I just dive in?
Please do.
OK.
Good.
Perfect.
So before we before I do that,
I want to kind of take a second and let
us all get here and arrive.
What we're talking about here isn't just
a qualifying condition or one more
diagnosis.
It's it's death, dying, grief,
end of life, bereavement, mortality.
And I would argue these are some of the
biggest things that that we process and
some of the biggest challenges that we
face as humans.
And so if we could just kind of take a
second to satisfied your To Do List,
set aside the things you have to do after
this meeting and the the things that came
before and let yourself be present for
the next hour or so together,
hour and a half together that very often
on online meetings,
it's really easy to multitask and be
doing lots of other things.
And so I just offer you this opportunity
to be here with each other now.
So with that, I'll get right in.
So who am I and why have I been asked to
to have this conversation with you today?
For a little bit of background about me,
I started my career as an EMT at the age
of 18.
So I've always worked in the medical
field.
I eventually went on to nursing school
and became an emergency room and trauma
nurse in California.
After graduating from Cal State,
he worked with my BSN.
And then in 2013,
I myself got really sick,
spent a long time in the hospital,
lots of major surgeries, dialysis, sepsis,
resuscitation,
all culminating in a near death
experience.
And it absolutely shattered my view and
paradigm of the world.
Took me several years to kind of process
that experience and integrate it.
And eventually what I came to is that I'm,
I'm here to be working in end of life
care, helping people through this process.
And so I do that in a couple of ways.
In 2022, I opened my private practice,
Conscious Crossroads End of Life Services,
where I work with clients through the
entire arc of end of life care.
I use the titles End of Life Guide,
death doula and Pure Grief Companion.
End of Life guide,
meaning that I work with folks that are
young and healthy and death is a way off
in the future and we're just doing
planning and kind of getting their ducks
in a row and, and processing death fears.
And then as a death doula,
I work with people who are at the stage
of palliative care, Hospice, active dying,
death.
And then as a pure grief companion,
I help their families and those left
behind through the the journey of grief.
And I use the,
the title peer grief companion because
I'm a peer.
I am not a licensed practitioner any
longer.
I do not hold an RN license.
I'm not a therapist or social worker.
I am just a peer who has received lots of
training and grief both formally and
through lived experience.
And so I campaign in people in the
process of their grief.
Last year I founded the New Mexico Death
Care Network,
which is a new nonprofit here in our
state that kind of serves 2 purposes.
We're a professional membership
organization that brings together those
that work in end of life care.
We offer networking opportunities and
education and things for each other
support there,
but then we offer an opportunity for
community members to find those services
through our website.
And then for those that can't afford and
non medical comprehensive end of life
support like that of a death doula,
we will actually pay for the provider
directly for those that can't afford the
services.
So say someone needed a death doula,
they can't afford it,
we pay the doula directly.
So we're effectively keeping good
providers in the field while offering
services to those that can't afford it.
And I'm telling you all of this to let
you know that I'm not an outsider looking
in on this program or on this topic,
that I'm somebody who will likely be
boots on the ground working alongside
with licensed clinicians helping
implement this program.
And so I think it's important that you
understand a little bit of background
about who I am and why I'm talking about
all this.
So today, what I hope to cover is first,
what's a death doula?
I think many people on this call
understand the role and the scope and the
distinction of death doulas from clinical
care, but I doubt everyone does,
and maybe some who listen to the
recording later won't.
So I want to make sure we cover that
first.
And then I want to cover the case for
death doulas being included in SB 219 in
the implementation of the program.
Why psilocybin needs continuity providers
such as death doulas?
I'll also offer kind of a model of care
like the doula continuum.
It's something that very much mirrors how
doulas work with folks at end of life and
how that can kind of seamlessly weave
into the arc of care throughout a
psilocybin preparation, dosing,
and integration experience.
And then there's some kind of hard
questions that I think are really
important to acknowledge and talk about
specifically scope, licensure,
liability and safety surrounding bringing
in additional supportive roles that are
unlicensed like that of a death doula.
And then some practical considerations
that I'd like us to kind of chat about
today and maybe questions we can bounce
back and forth and things to continue
kind of noodling on as we move forward.
So first I want to acknowledge that this
is not anything new.
Not everybody is familiar with death
doulas,
but this is an ancient tradition and this
is just the modern resurgence and kind of
the modern iteration of it as becoming a
profession.
Indigenous cultures have held positions
such as a death doula forever, right?
Medicine people, elders, wisdom keepers,
kid and dead as shamans,
all every kind of iteration of this
possible.
The word doula itself is ancient Greek
and it means a woman who helps or serves,
or one who mothers the mother.
So very often you hear about doulas in
terms of birth or lactation or postpartum
doulas and death Doulas use the same
title because there are so many
similarities between birth and death.
The way I like to explain it is that all
of the work and the effort and the pain
of labouring life into the world falls on
our mothers on our way out of the world.
All of that work and that effort,
that labor process falls on us.
And so very often the same work and prep,
preparation, excuse me,
that you want to offer for a woman doing
the hard work of bringing life into the
world is the same type of preparation and,
and environment that you want to create
for a person who's doing the hard work of
leaving the world.
And so doulas work in kind of multiple
areas.
Emotionally,
we're helping people hold grief and fear
and process anticipatory loss.
Existentially.
It's it's talking with clients about life
reviews, right?
What's the theme of your life story?
What is all of this been about and how
can we maybe document it through
something like a legacy project or
letters to your loved ones Relationally,
families preparing for folks stopping
treatment or maybe entering Hospice,
having difficult conversations amongst
family members where maybe values don't
match up.
That's a lot of what doulas do,
advocating for our client,
the person who is dying and making sure
that their wishes are heard amongst
everyone in the family or in their system,
their care circle.
And practically,
it's a lot of helping navigate through
the entire process and journey of end of
life.
Making sure that the paperwork is done.
You know, all of the boxes are checked,
what I call the business of death that
your advance directives, your most,
your will, your trusts,
your beneficiaries and transfer on death
forms.
All of those things are taken care of and
the after plans as well, right?
What do you want to happen to your dead
body?
How do you plan for your memorial?
What ways can we honor you that are
unique and important and important to you
and your family?
And so doulas kind of work in all of
those areas.
And there's often a lot of overlap
between clinical roles or between Hospice
roles and what a doula does.
A doula does some of the things that a
social worker might do.
They have some of the spiritual
conversations that a chaplain or
spiritual advisor might have.
Sometimes a doula will sit and offer some
respite care so that the loved one can go
out and go to the grocery store,
similar to what a Hospice volunteer might
offer.
And so there's lots of overlap there.
And I think the distinction is that
doulas are the same, the same face,
the same continuous person through the
entire journey with the client and a
family.
And that's really important to those who
are going through such a scary and
profound time.
So it's important to note that doulas are
not clinicians.
And when I say clinician,
I'm not just talking about physicians,
I'm talking about any licensed
practitioner.
So social workers, therapists, counselors,
nurses, physicians, nurse practitioners,
P as everybody in between, right,
licensed clinicians.
So we are not that we are continuity
providers.
So we hold the whole arc of before,
during and after a clinical intervention
or before, during and after a death,
right?
The preparation,
the actual vigil time and then grief
support afterwards.
So doulas are kind of prime to be that
continuity piece throughout a,
a medicine or psilocybin experience as
well.
So the licensed clinician is primarily
there for episodic care, right?
There's preparation sessions,
the dosing session,
integration sessions where the doula
would may be there for continuous care.
I've had clients that I've worked with
for 18 months before they passed away,
seeing them weekly for a couple of hours
a week and that time actually increasing
and then actually being there through the
the death itself.
A clinician may be focused specifically
on the psilocybin experience and what
that may offer as a clinical intervention
for an end of life patient.
Where the doula will be focused on the
entire end of life journey of not just
the person dying but their family as well.
The licensed clinician is primarily there
with clinical responsibility and they
hold that liability.
Where the doula is there more
relationally working more on existential
and psychosocial support,
The licensed clinician will be bound by
the program structure and Department of
Health rules as well as their scope of
practice legally within their licensure.
And a doula's got a more flexible home
community based presence.
It's kind of a a paid friend, if you will,
someone to be there through the entire
arc of the journey with you.
And obviously a licensed clinician has
got their medical or psychological
training requirements and we need to kind
of talk about what the requirements may
be for a doula in this role.
As far as just out there working as a
doula,
there are many training programs and and
certification programs out there.
So do we need to look at accrediting
specific doula training programs,
How we need to kind of talk about what
that will look like for us?
But right now it's generally there's some
sort of end of life training in addition
to lived relational experience.
And that's a huge distinction between
doulas and licensed clinicians.
So I think it's really important to
acknowledge like what a landmark piece of
legislation SB219 is,
the fact that we're only the third in the
country that's working on this psilocybin
Medical Psilocybin Act.
But we're the only ones that have the end
of life care provision in here.
However,
it's not defined about what exactly that
means.
It's kind of up to the Department of
Health Advisory Board to come up with the
definition of end of life care and who
those patients are,
what that timeline is and what that looks
like.
And so we have this really great
opportunity because within that,
that means we also have to define what
the care team is composed of and what
that looks like,
what support rolls are open.
And so I think it's really important now
that we name the role of the death doula
or the end of life doula,
because if it isn't named in the rules,
it effectively doesn't exist in
implementation.
Systems tend to default to what is
actually written in words.
And so I think it's important that we
define it now both in what the role is
and what it is not,
so that it's covered and that there's
clarity and recognition of the role
boundaries around the role and that will
lead to safety.
There we go.
So this is kind of that doula continuum
of care that I was talking about.
And you can kind of overlap this,
this arc of care with the actual dying
process itself.
Here we're looking at working within a
psilocybin program,
but I would argue that death itself is
kind of the ultimate journey or the
ultimate ceremony,
and that every other medicine experience
that one has prior to death is prepping
us for that one.
And so this whole arc looks exactly the
same whether we're talking about a
medicine experience or the actual dying
experience.
And so the before doula's help again with
life Review, legacy work,
lots of questions like what's the theme
of your life story?
Ben, what are you the most proud of?
What are your biggest regrets Diving into
that and,
and finding places and ways to
acknowledge that story and memorialize
that story for people through legacy
projects.
We're a clinician may come in and have a
a diagnosing tool that they can use,
a clinical tool that will help them
determine, yes,
this person is experiencing existential
distress or death anxiety.
And it's a box that is checked,
a code that is put into a system in order
for a reimbursement.
But a doula will be the one sitting there
walking people through meditation
exercises to help process that fear of
death,
the one holding their hands through the
actual death process itself.
So there's a lot of fear and meaning make
meaning making processing that happens on
the the prep side for doulas,
intention setting versus clinical goal
setting is big.
How do we even tend to feel at the end of
this process?
What are your goals there instead of just
a clinical goal?
We can also help prep family, right?
Explaining to family that.
Your,
your person is likely to come out of this
experience different and how that may
look in your relationship and in their
processing of their,
their experience moving forward.
And then also making sure that we're
bringing cultural and spiritual context
to everything.
And that's different for each person.
Doulos are specifically trained in
meeting people where they are and
honoring their their cultural and belief
systems as they are without influencing
them or bringing our own stuff into the
picture during the experience of itself.
Doulas can be a trusted and familiar
presence because again,
we've we've likely been with this family
and with this client through the process
of even determining if they want to seek
out a psilocybin experience and then
helping them find a practitioner to help
them through the process.
So we can be a a very familiar face in an
altered state,
which can be extremely helpful.
Again,
we're already trained in the non clinical
vigil support and in my experience,
facilitating A deathbed space,
A deathbed vigil is very similar to
holding space and supporting someone
through a medicine experience.
Again,
this cultural and ritual holding is
something to list you all day every day.
That's kind of our bread and butter
offering comfort and grounding cues,
which are again are often the same types
of cues that are offered during actual
active dying time as well.
And again,
just having continuity through the
altered state,
that familiar presence after for
integration,
helping translate these insights into
action,
where very often you may receive some
sort of insight that now it's like, oh,
I need to repair my relationship with
with this person.
A doula may be there through the entire
process of what that looks like for this
person and this family.
And now maybe the reintegration of a
family member into the family system that
might happen, say at the deathbed space.
And a doula may be that continuous person
there that's through the entire process
with that family.
So translating the,
the insights that you received into
action in your life,
how does it change how you process your,
your deathbed experience or your
relational experiences with those around
you?
And again, legacy project support,
it's not just about saying, yes,
legacy projects would be good for you.
This is something I recommend you do,
but actually actively helping clients do
those processes, those projects,
helping again with family debriefing,
just being there through integration
processes with the clinician and then
continuing that afterwards.
And again,
that continued emotional processing over
time because we're likely to be the ones
continuing the relationship through death
and then beyond the psilocybin experience
itself.
But at active dying time.
What better source of comfort than the
person who was also there with you during
your psilocybin experience is now that
same energy, presence,
and face that you see as you are actively
leaving the world.
Doulas are also great for family
bereavement care,
as I've already mentioned,
and post to death guidance,
guiding families through ceremony and
ritual in the presence of their loved
ones,
dead body spending as much time as they
may need.
And that can even look like holding home
funerals.
So many different things that doulas can
offer in the post death space.
And then again,
just community grief support.
So doulas in the the pre the preparation
section of this, this process,
I guess that you could call it,
I think are extremely important.
We're all,
we're all very aware that psilocybin
outcomes are completely dependent on set
and setting and doulas are trained in
this terrain.
That's exactly what we do is set,
set and setting.
We have been trained to treat death as a
sacred event.
And so setting up everyone's mindset of
how they enter that deathbed space is
very similar to how everyone you set up
someone that's entering A psilocybin or a
medicine space.
Again,
talking about life review and narrative
reflection ahead of time,
processing fears and helping let people
let things go,
helping them articulate their intentions,
not just their goals.
Helping prepare family for possible
psychological and spiritual shifts.
And really important is the cultural and
spiritual context setting.
Jen talked about this a ton last time and
I think that's, that's absolutely key,
especially in the end of life space for
folks.
So as far as the policy goes,
this is important because it'll help
improve safety and reduce risk of
distress during the sessions.
Because again,
there's been this continuous person that
has helped them walk through all of this
prep beyond just that one or two sessions
that may be covered under the the program
itself.
And it extends beyond what clinicians
actually have time and bandwidth for,
just like all parts of our medical system,
palliative care, Hospice care,
that those medical teams are stretched
incredibly thin and they don't have the
the space to see clients for extended
long preparation and integration sessions
before and after a journey.
And so we can also kind of help the eyes
and ears to help the clinical team assess
cultural gaps,
things that we may be missing because
again,
the clinicians and the medical team don't
have the time to spend that a doula might.
And then this reduces the burden on
licensed facilitators and clinicians.
So if doulas are working alongside
licensed clinicians that that combination
can offer so much more to a patient and a
family than just the the clinical process
of medicine.
And so I think integration again is where
doulas can be the most essential.
If we only treat this as a clinical
intervention,
it will be effective and we will miss out
on a lot of opportunity for the patient
and the family.
Without long term integration,
the insights may not translate into
actual action.
And so where doulas can do is help,
like we said earlier,
actually move things into real life
concrete actions that make a difference
in how they not only live the rest of the
time they're here,
but what their death looks like and how
their family ends up processing the grief
afterwards.
So the key distinctions from clinicians
where we're translating insights into end
of life decisions,
it's not just the psychological
processing, it's the real life.
Yeah.
I keep saying it,
but the real life concrete actions the
world can also help support repair of
relationships and that presence extends
to active death and bereavement.
We're holding those legacy projects
through to completion so that they're
actually delivered to family members
before or after the person dies.
It is non clinical.
We are not diagnosing,
We are not treating it as non directive.
We help bridge the mystical experience
into practical life closure.
And so again,
it's relationship based over time.
It's not episodic.
So it's not just coming in for a clinical
intervention.
It's continuing throughout the entire arc
of care.
Another big thing to talk about is that
especially here in New Mexico,
we've got a very large rural population,
a large indigenous population,
and a large low income population.
So doulas can help extend the reach of
the program.
Excluding doulas risks creating a program
that's clinically sound and socially
unacceptable or inaccessible,
which is unacceptable.
That was a Freudian slip.
It's always been a big challenge to me
that even doula work is something that
very quickly could become only available
to a small percentage of the population.
And I think all of us in this room are
really aware of the fact that psychedelic
work and psilocybin work is very quickly
kind of becoming another one of those
things.
So bringing doulas in can kind of help
mitigate some of that risk.
So we can be community navigators for
rural New Mexico patients.
So people that are way out that may have
a hard time waiting for a clinician or
seeing a clinician on a regular basis,
perhaps there's a doula in that area or a
doula willing to travel to that area.
And it would be much less expensive to to
cover that cost.
We can also work as kind of cultural
translators and and navigators between
indigenous communities,
which are very often these low income
rural indigenous communities have very
good reason to be distrustful of medical
systems.
And so having a layperson,
someone outside of the system helping
navigate and translate can help kind of
bridge that gap and increase trust and
comfort.
Comfort with the system.
Again,
using plain language and informed consent
types of support,
which lowers the barrier of access to the
program.
Then doulas also help extend family and
caregiver support.
Doulas are specifically trained to not
just work with the person that's dying,
but their care circle as well.
That's part of of what we're taught to do
from the very beginning.
And so we can help prepare families for
the client or patients possible changes
in worldview,
helping them interpret their paid their
their loved ones experience.
We are experts in helping reduce
caregiver anxiety and confusion through a
sense of grounding support,
but also education.
I think education is absolutely key to
reducing anxiety throughout the end of
life process,
both for the person that's leaving and
for their care circle.
And then we're also again,
already trained in facilitating these
challenging conversations that may come
up post session.
And then again,
we can provide bereavement continuity.
I find working with my clients that they,
they find it a lot of comfort in talking
to me about their grief because they know
that I knew their loved 1 and I may have
even been present when they took their
last breath,
which can feel incredibly supportive to
someone as opposed to coming in and
talking to a complete stranger about
someone that you've lost.
So kind of the harder questions and the
things that I think that are really
important to acknowledge and that are
really important for me to kind of help
us tease apart and figure out coming from
a medical side of things,
coming from a career where I was licensed
and I was in a regulated industry,
it's really important that we define the
role of a doula within this program.
And so some of the concerns are scope
creep and clinical overlap.
And so a proposed safeguard there would
be that we explicitly define the non
clinical role of a death doula.
Again, what we do and what we do not do,
what is permitted is what is not
permitted.
The fact that we are not licensed as
doulas and I don't think I mentioned that
in the very beginning, I apologize.
Doulas are certified through whatever
training program that they took.
There is currently no overarching
regulatory body or licensure for doulas.
It's almost similar to a life coach where
almost anyone can call themselves a life
coach.
So it's going to be really important to
put in place some competency based
training requirements and as some sort of
a voluntary registry of these folks that
have gone through whatever approved
training programs.
There is some precedence for this and
we'll talk about it a little bit more
later through Birth Doulas where there
are multiple different tracks through
which they can be certified in order to
receive reimbursement through Medicaid.
And we'll dive into that a little bit
more in a moment.
There's also some overlap with the role
of the clinician,
the licensed practitioner here.
And so again,
it'll be really important to clearly
differentiate in our language the role of
the clinician versus a doula or non
licensed support person.
And the fact that that the clinician's
role is generally episodic where this non
licensed support person,
the death doula is a longitudinal
relationship that continues throughout
the entire arc of end of life concerns
around liability and accountability.
Again,
it's gonna be really important to make
this a team based care model so that the
non licensed person is never working on
their own or facilitating on their own.
That they are always working either under
or alongside a a licensed clinician,
That it is a team based model and that
there's very clear informed consent
language throughout.
And then the other big concerns are
patient vulnerability and safety.
And again,
that supervision coordination with the
care team will be really important.
But then also having some sort of
escalation protocols in place, you know,
if something did go wrong,
where does the community member go?
Where does the patient complain to kind
of thing?
Because again,
if there's no overarching regulatory body,
there's got to be some sort of oversight
in place.
So doulas are not new to healthcare
adjacent roles.
There are lots of established unlicensed
non clinical roles that are well accepted
in healthcare and reimbursed through
healthcare programs or government
programs.
Lots of examples listed here.
Community health workers, birth doulas,
peer support specialists and patient
navigators using peer support specialists
as an example.
Those are folks that are lay people who
have generally gone through something
themselves,
either substance abuse and recovery or
mental health issues and recovery there.
And then they go through a 40 hour
training program where now they can go
out and support people who are going
through the same types of issues that
they've already gone through.
And that role is state recognized.
There's a competency based credential and
a listing of those folks.
So I can see death doulas ending up in a
very similar situation.
Or for example,
birth doulas are currently covered by New
Mexico,
Medicaid and several other States and
there are very clear tracks for their
certification,
for reimbursement or for eligibility in
that program.
There are accredited training schools
that you can choose to have gone through
and that's one of the tracks for
certification or for eligibility rather
for reimbursement.
There's also a, you know,
kind of a community member,
like a full Keeler sort of person that
has been doing this for years and years
and years and a licensed clinician just
writes a couple of letters of of
reference.
So there are different ways of that,
not certifying or creating eligibility or
acknowledging that these people have
received the competency based training
that's necessary.
We've tested them in it and we
acknowledge that they are acceptable to
go out and do this work in the world.
So we don't have to reinvent the wheel.
We can look to a lot of these other
unlicensed roles and healthcare to,
to figure out exactly how to do this with
Death dual as well.
So I'm going to go over this slide really
quickly.
But my whole point here is that there's
lots of evidence that psilocybin is
helpful at end of life, right?
We've got the NYU and John Hopkins trials
that show significant reductions in death
anxiety and depression.
You know,
Doctor Lehman's done lots of studies,
currently working on lots of studies.
There's tons of evidence that it works
and that it helps.
There's also a fair amount of of evidence
out there at the moment.
Not enough,
not enough studies have been done,
but that death dual is also do something
similar that there's an improvement in
quality of life, reduction and anxiety,
increased sense of control for the dying
patients,
consistent evidence that there's benefit
to family and caregivers.
And the point is that here in New Mexico
with this program,
we have an amazing opportunity to show if
we collect the right data,
the evidence that bringing these two
modalities together,
what death doulas can offer at end of
life along with psilocybin experiences.
Then what can we bring together to show
that?
What evidence can we collect to show the
the benefit of bringing these two to to
dying clients?
And I think the evidence will be really
clear very quickly just in what I've seen
personally, anecdotally, anecdotally.
And so I wanted to kind of just pay
attention to that and kind of maybe think
about what we can,
what data we can start collecting now.
We're in a really amazing position here.
So I don't want to waste it.
So these three practical considerations
moving forward,
everything we've talked about so far is
just kind of in context,
but what do we do with that?
So we know what death stool is,
Do we know kind of how psilocybin can
help an end of life,
how death doulas can help at life and
then what?
So again,
recognition creates clarity and clarity
creates safety.
The first step I think is defining the
role of the doula in this setting,
that it's non clinical, non directive,
non licensed end of life support and that
we should be a permitted presence
throughout the psilocybin experience as
long as that's what the the client slash
patient wants.
And then at at the clinician's discretion
as well.
But that we're there for the preparation
sessions,
we're there during administration,
we're there for the integration sessions
and we'll likely be the ones that are
there at the deathbed vigil where the
clinician likely won't be.
That's just not generally how it goes.
We need to define explicit boundaries,
right?
What the doula does not do,
and it's not permitted to do that.
There is no clinical assessment and
diagnosis.
There's not psychotherapy,
there's no medical care,
there's no administration of medications,
on and on, right with it,
with that's all explicitly laid out.
And then there's got to be coordination
protocol and required communication with
licensed clinicians on the care team.
And then I think we need to create a
lightweight doula participation pathway
that it's got a low barrier to entry,
but it's very clear good boundaries that
it's not licensure because that will
limit access and exclude workforce
diversity.
So there needs to be many minimum
training criteria.
We've talked about that a little bit.
There are multiple doula training
programs out there,
and what kind type of specific
psychedelic psilocybin training do we
need our to require for our dualism in
this role?
That we need to create some sort of a
voluntary registry system similar to what
we've got for community health workers.
We need to form a code of ethics around
death doulas in the psilocybin space.
One of the things that we can look to
here is the National End of Life Doula
Alliance, or Anita.
They do offer a professional membership
organization for end of life doulas and
they do offer a short exam that one can
take and get a proficiency badge.
So that at least says I understand the
scope of practice.
I understand the legality surrounding my
role.
I understand, you know,
cultural competence,
the the basics of what it means to be a
death doula out there doing this work in
a safe manner.
And so do we create something similar
right where there's a testing system and
a certification that says that yes,
I understand all of the roles of a doula
and a psychedelic support person and I'm
approved to do this work in New Mexico.
And then again,
creating accountability mechanisms.
So obviously any doulas working within
this,
it would have to agree to whatever the
program guidelines are.
I think we should have background checks
there.
Grievance processes need to be put in
place and that all of that needs to be
proportional to the non clinical role.
We need to recognize that we can't be
charging doulas $10,
000 for training programs when they're
never going to recoup that ROI based on
what they can actually charge clients.
So we need to be realistic about what
we're asking of people in this role as
well.
This one,
this is more just kind of me and my ideas
that I want to throw all of this out
there.
But I think it's really,
really important to note that equity is
not just access to the substance or the
medicine itself.
It's access to all of the support that
makes psilocybin meaningful and safe.
And it will actually result in concrete
action and change for this human in life
and death.
So we already have the treatment equity
fund.
You know,
Doctor Lehman and I talked about that a
little bit and that's kind of been
satisfied specifically for the medicine.
And that's great.
What other funds or what other systems
can we come up where we make to Stoola
services explicitly eligible?
Is there a per patient stipend that helps
enrolled doulas within the program that
prioritizes rural and low income
underserved patients?
I just want us to be open to thinking
about what something like that might look
like.
And then I think it, you know,
pilot programs and grants,
like there's something for the research
fund already,
including doula integrated care models in
our pilot research and then tracking
specific, specific outcomes, right?
Was there an improvement in death anxiety
with a doula versus without a doula or
before the doula versus after the doula
was brought in?
Same with family satisfaction scores,
care utilization.
I think that if we did some good research,
we would likely find that there are a lot
less utilization of even the Hospice
nurses and Hospice resources when you
have a good doula relationship in a
family as a person is dying.
And then for the concrete kind of action
steps,
does it help once you you bring in
someone like a doula or you've had the
psilocybin experience?
Do people get their their paperwork done?
Do they do their advanced care planning?
Do they get their most finished and their
wills done because they now have this
different level of acceptance of their
own impermanence?
So I think examining some of those things
and making sure we have some funding for
that research will be really helpful.
And including doulas in some of those
metrics and then bundled care models.
Do we start to include doula services as
reimbursable support there?
Again,
there's precedence already for this birth
doulas.
I think death doulas are probably 20
years behind birth doulas as far as
getting policy in place and,
and lobbying and, and all of those things.
But again,
we're in a really unique position here
with this program.
So could this be a pilot for the rest of
the country?
Some of the the metrics like I mentioned
earlier that I think we should kind of be
looking at patient death anxiety scores,
completion of advanced care planning,
families, caregiver satisfaction,
psychological distress,
post session program,
access by demographic.
I think this is going to be really
important for us to pay attention to.
Is this only being utilized by upper
middle class people in the central part
of the state here in Albuquerque?
Or do we have real access and real
utilization by our more rural indigenous
and low income communities?
And then care coordination, equality,
the Duala clinician team communication.
So that was a whole lot of stuff.
But to just sum it up really clearly and
really succinctly, I think as doulas,
what we're kind of looking for within
this program is that number one,
we define the role so that it is
acknowledged within the program and that
it gets implemented and that it is safe,
that we create a pathway for training and
oversight so that we're accountable and
accessible.
And then there's got to be some sort of
funding of the role because the reality
is if we don't include that,
somewhere along the line,
it's going to turn into asking doulas to
volunteer their time at.
And that just becomes exploitative over
time.
It's just one more way of, yeah,
not honoring the caring, nurturing,
non licensed roles in our society.
And so to kind of sum up everything that
I'm I'm kind of trying to bring here is
that if this program is only designed
around the clinical moment,
it'll definitely work.
There will be positive outcomes for
people, no doubt.
We know that about psilocybin in and of
itself,
but it will only partially work if we
include structured non clinical care like
death doulas.
This program has the potential to not
just transform how we experience medicine,
but how we experience dying and how we
experience living the last however many
months we have on this planet if we're in
an end of life spot.
So with all of that,
I am here for questions.
I hope we that sparked a whole lot of
questions and a lot of conversation.
And my, my contact information is there.
You can get me through either one of
those websites and I I,
I hope we we have lots more to come.
All right.
Thank you, Danielle.
Larry,
did you have anything to say before we
take some questions for attendees?
Yeah, Yeah, Daniel, first of all,
Danielle, that that was a great talk.
And even having seen your slides and
watched it another time,
it was really great.
So I really appreciate all of that.
I may have one or two questions,
Maybe I'll pop in before before we open.
One is,
and I hope this isn't too specific
question,
but as we're looking at like the finances
of what, what it what, what would it cost?
I mean, how does it work?
I mean, in other words,
you obviously when people hire death
doula,
they don't know how long they're going to
be living for it.
How how is how is the Billings done?
And if we're thinking about trying to get
that covered, Yeah.
So as far as working with a doula and in
their private practice,
every doula does it differently and so
everybody charges a different amount.
Some people will do it hourly,
some people do it as a bundle or packages.
I personally offer either an hourly rate
or you can purchase a bundle of 10 hours
upfront for a discounted rate and then
once those hours are used,
we continue with the discounted rate.
Now as far as how we reimburse through
the New Mexico Death Care Network,
because we have limited funds,
we have a very nominal hourly freight fee
of $50 per hour.
But each provider can be reimbursed at
$50 per hour for up to 30 hours per
client and two clients per calendar year
that we hope will offer a good amount of
supportive time for a client and a family
that likely will not cover all of the
hours, all of the time.
And it's, again, it's a nominal amount,
$50.00 an hour,
but it's what we can do at the moment.
And it's also modeled after the the
reimbursement program for birth doulas
where birth doulas are allowed up to
$1500 per patient through a birth doula,
like through a, a labor delivery process.
So we tried to kind of model things that
way.
And I think that we can look to that
reimbursement program and do something
similar.
And y'all, why?
Why only two clients a year?
Like what's the rationale behind that
trying to limit so that one person isn't
taking all of the funds because the funds
are so limited.
We are currently only,
we're completely privately funded.
We haven't received any grants or
anything yet.
So we're on a very limited budget.
So that was the rationale.
Hopefully we'll be able to open it up to
make it unlimited someday.
And then another question is, you know,
and this will come up in other meetings,
you know,
we've talked about this is end of life
care,
but that having an expensive care on that.
In other words, you can be diagnosed with,
you know,
stage 3 breast cancer and have a,
you know, estimated lifespan of two years,
but but you're still in a grieving
process and that end of life care with
psilocybin therapy would be appropriate.
I'm curious if you think there's any role
for, you know,
death ruler and somebody in that,
in that situation.
I think absolutely, yes.
I, I work with clients at,
at all different ages and, and stages.
I have several clients right now who are
undergoing treatment, right.
They've just gotten some sort of
diagnosis and those folks would be
absolutely primed for a program like this
helping them process their diagnosis,
their treatment,
what it means like how to to work with
their bodies.
All of these things could be extremely
helpful for those who are just diagnosed
and not at end of life yet.
And then as far as grief goes,
I think that after an initial period of
time,
and that time will be different for every
human, there will.
There's no prescribed time.
That's correct.
But after a time of initial processing
and fresh grief and you've kind of moved
through some of those very natural
organic stages,
I think that a psilocybin journey and
experience can be incredibly helpful for
people continuing to process grief.
Yeah.
One more question then I'll I'll quit
asking questions.
Do you think that we should be requiring
that that at least for reimbursement or
or involvement that the death rule has
passed the Anita exam?
Is that like a you know,
Jen mentioned that in in her in order to
see what you thought about that and also
what's involved in that.
We, you mentioned that you,
we don't want people to have to spend a
$10,000 program.
Is Anita,
what's involved in like studying for the
NITA exam and taking it?
It's, it's a fairly short exam.
It's a pretty simple, for the most part.
I think it was 100 questions or something
like that really nominal fee.
I think it was a $50 entrance fee.
And then you,
their membership is 50 or $100 a year.
So again, it's very nominal prices.
They don't offer a specific training
school.
NITA does not.
They just offer this proficiency exam and
since they are the closest thing we
currently have to a regulatory body,
right,
they're just a professional membership
organization,
but they've kind of taken up the lead for
establishing codes of ethics and scope of
practice.
And so they are the the best we have at
the moment for sure.
And so in short of creating our own
testing and licensure or certification
system, yes,
I think that they are a great place to
start is requiring at least needed
proficiency.
And y'all thanks for asking,
answering all my questions.
We have a few thanks for good questions,
few other people's questions.
Thank you.
All right, sounds good.
We will go to the attendees And again,
for folks who would like to ask questions
you there is a icon in the top left part
of teams that says raise that has a
little hand.
I mean you can go ahead and click that if
you'd like to ask a good question.
So it looks like first we've got Hannah
Rose and Hannah, I have enabled your mic.
You can talk when you're ready.
Yeah, I believe.
Oh, wow.
My hand was raised.
I did not mean to have my hand raised
because my questions were pretty much
answered in the chat.
So yeah,
I I was just curious about dual roles in
the program as a a death doula and as a
clinician.
And then once I have my social work
degree, then also as a social worker.
But that will be clarified in the future
in other meetings.
Thank you.
Sweet.
Thanks, Hannah.
Oh, yeah.
And I guess other reminder for folks, if,
if you could also just like introduce
yourself and if you're a resident and
have any affiliations as well.
And so next we have Clifford Reese.
Clifford, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute and speak when you're
ready.
I mean, again, to do that,
the mic icon is at the top right part of
the banner in Teams.
If you click that,
you should be able to unmute.
Got it.
Yeah.
My raised hand is on the the upper right
too, not the upper left, but that's fine.
I'm,
I'm still learning six years after the
pandemic.
My name is Clifford Reese.
Introduction.
I'm a retired Department of Health
attorney,
spent 23 years with the department,
left the department in 2004,
but worked on medical cannabis in 2000
through my departure from the department.
The last 20 years or so,
I've worked seasonally during legislative
sessions for the state legislature,
and in particular,
I was Senator Jeff Steinborn's
legislative analyst during the 2025
session when the Medical Psilocybin Act
was passed.
I have two observations.
If I can call you, Danielle.
Excellent, excellent presentation.
And I'm coming from the legal perspective,
so this is not meant to be criticism,
but what is a suggestion for all of us?
And I hope the staff is listening.
I don't give legal advice to the
Department of Health staff anymore,
but it's a hard habit to break.
After 23 years,
I would stop referring to the statute as
SB.
What was it 219?
Because every year there's an SB-219-I
would start calling it the what it what
its short title is,
which is the Medical Psilocybin Act.
And if you want to,
we can put in parenthesis laws of 2025,
chapter 73.
And this is in the New Mexico statutes
annotated because we're talking about a
very specific Senate Bill 219 henceforth.
So let's not let's not create confusion.
Let's educate the public who we want to
reach.
And again, this is not a criticism.
This is just the lawyer observation.
The second part is an interpret.
I have a different interpretation,
Danielle,
of what you think should be in the rules
versus not in the rules.
Of course,
the statute authorizes the rule making
process.
So statutes have legal impact effect just
like the rules have legal impact,
just like the statute,
because it's based on a statute,
a delegation of authority in the Medical
Psilocybin Act to the Department of
Health.
And what you presented, as I heard it,
and please correct me if I didn't
understand you,
was you wanted a very detailed rule to
cover most of the things that concern you
about how the program will be implemented.
There's pros and cons to that.
The Pro is that it's clear what the
department intends through rulemaking,
which intentionally is not in statute
because the department has the expertise
and that's why it has the rulemaking
authority to fill in the details.
The con is the counter argument is if
something is not in the rule,
then it can be argued that it's not
specifically prohibited by the statute or
rules.
What I'm thinking about,
and this is based on my medical cannabis
experience,
is this field of medicine is changing
rapidly.
I think we would probably agree
philosophically anyway.
And so if we have a very detailed rule
and medically things change,
the department would need to go back
through the legal rulemaking process and
amend the rule.
If there's a bit of flexibility there,
that wouldn't be necessary and the
department could issue policy decisions
based on its interpretation of the
statute and rule.
So it's really a question more for staff
perhaps, Danielle,
but that's just how I see it as an over
the hill retired public health attorney.
But thank you very much for your
presentation.
I have also followed very closely the
Elizabeth Whitfield End of Life Act that
was enacted in 2019.
And I used the short title.
And I know my great colleague and friend
Barrick Wolf is on this and he was,
he and his colleagues were instrumental
in getting that passed.
And that really, I think,
has opened the door today.
So thank you for your presentation and
I'd be glad to hear your comment or
anyone else's comment on what I just said.
A little bit windy,
but habits are hard to break when you're
an attorney.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for that.
But First off,
the education on the SB 219 part,
I wasn't even aware that that changed and
it would be repeated yearly.
So thank you for that.
That's good for me.
Just knowledge moving forward.
And yeah, it's it, it's interesting.
And this this has come up for me just
recently with even the nonprofit as we
were forming everything and, you know,
making sure you put enough in your bylaws
to be clear,
but not too much that it's confining and,
and that back and forth and and whatnot.
And I think that my perspective came from
that place of wanting to make sure that
this this role is somehow integrated into
this this program that non licensed
support people are acknowledged,
accounted for and honored for,
for what we bring to the table and
acknowledging.
I think a big part of that is that death
is not a medical event.
A lot of medical stuff happens around
death,
and a lot of clinical support and
intervention is useful and necessary,
but it's a community event.
And so how do we make provisions for
honoring that part of it in a clinical
setting?
And I don't know what the right way to do
any of that is.
And I'm definitely not a lawyer,
so I value your perspective.
All right,
looks like next we've got Chris Caldwell.
Chris, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Hi all, Danielle, that was fabulous.
Thank you.
This is Chris Caldwell,
founder and director of End of Life
Psychedelic Care.
And some of you know that one of the
reasons why I founded the nonprofit was
to bring the voices of Dulas Antlens into
this world.
And so I have a few comments,
and I have a question for you, Danielle,
or whomever.
And I do want to tell one quick story.
OK.
So a couple of years ago we was working
with Michael from Palliative Medicines
physician in New in Northern California.
And we paired him with a doula.
And one of the stories she shared was
that, and Michael is a fabulous physician,
but when he left and she was there and
like you're talking about,
you build the trust,
he let his hair down so he wasn't talking
to the doctor.
So I absolutely love the, you know,
the role of a doula.
So a couple of other things,
just so all of you know what I've been
working on by the way,
end of life psychedelic care has the only
end of life doula that has a plant
medicine component, quote UN quote.
It's not a training for for psilocybin
facilitation,
but it does prepare you for the NITA
you're talking about, Danielle.
And obviously it's not for any doula,
but for anybody else like a social worker,
therapist,
a physician who may in fact want to learn
more about end of life processes.
So this year we are group program like
Inelda's actually if you're familiar with
that,
but I won't go into what that is right
now.
One of the things we are doing to your
point to Danielle,
we received a grant to do home based
ketamine and spiritual care.
So this is ketamine,
but we are pairing an end of life doula
or chaplain or minister with a palliative
medicine physician dose our first patient
next month.
We are building that process you're
talking about and we obviously will have
some data.
It's only 15 patients that we can't we're
supporting under this grant.
But by the end of the year we'll have
some data for you guys and then I think
let's see.
I think that's it.
The question I have for you though,
is when you're talking about a doula
being a part of a team,
are you talking about in person
supervision by a clinician or are you
talking about remote supervision by a
clinician?
You know, I think that's,
that's kind of up in the air at the
moment.
I,
I fully believe that doulas are with the
proper training,
perfect people to be in person
facilitators and, and support people.
And a clinician could be doing remote
support.
You know, that they are there for the,
the prep and the integration and,
and maybe even there remotely.
But we've got a lot of really far out
rural areas around here and say somebody,
you know,
way down in Silver City that's at end of
life and,
and homebound and maybe a Hospice patient
needs these services.
It may be much more realistic to count on
a non licensed support person to,
to be there during that that dosing
session than having to wait for a
licensed clinician.
And so I think that that's open to the
committee and the board to continue
talking about.
But again, we're,
we're already facilitating these very
challenging altered experiences,
such as the deathbed space.
And we're doing that without physicians.
We're doing that without nurses.
We're doing that without any of these
licensed or medical supervision at
deathbed spaces.
And this is extremely similar.
Extremely similar.
Yeah.
Well, you, you know,
I wholeheartedly support that.
And if there's anything I can do to to
pull it, we've got some data,
but from a psychedelic death worker study
we did as well that if you want to,
if you want to set up a time to talk.
You also remind me when you were talking
about the prepper sort of roles that a
doula could fulfill,
one of the things we talk about all the
time is the the benefit of integrative
practices, whether that's reishi,
you know,
for somebody who's trained but guided
visualizations, yeah,
like supportive of meditations,
breathing exercises, reishi, gentle yoga,
restorative yoga and and stuff.
And you know,
we have doulas doing that all the time,
especially when psychedelics may not be
called for at a certain stage of life.
So, yeah, thank.
Thank you, though.
Thank you for excellent work.
Excuse me.
I would love to connect.
All right, let's see.
It looks like next we've got Clifford
Reese again.
Let's see.
All right, Clifford,
I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Thank you very much.
And I'd appreciate,
I thank you for the opportunity to ask a
follow up question.
Certainly want people to have an
opportunity for their first question.
Danielle, let me ask you this.
You talked about licensure and lack of
licensure.
Do you personally favor licensure of
death doulas by either the Department of
Health or the Regulation and Licensing
department,
knowing the hoops that one needs to go
through when the executive branch issues
a license to practice a profession?
This has been a a big topic of discussion
and something that I've personally
wrestled with quite a bit.
Again,
coming from the more medical side of
things and, and licensure.
And the answer is no.
I think that the the main benefit of
doulas is that we are outside of the
system.
We are supporting the system,
we are adjacent to the system,
but we're outside of the healthcare and
medical system.
And that's what gives us our relational
power with a family.
And it's a different level of,
of trust that can be developed.
I very often work with folks that tell me
things like,
I don't want to tell the social worker
this.
I don't want to talk to a chaplain,
but I'm just a, a doula, right?
I'm just a girl coming in to talk to you.
And that allows us to,
to develop things on a completely
different level.
It also allows us to maintain our role as
the client advocate without any sort of
conflict of interest.
It is always my primary role that
regardless of of what's happening, say a,
a, a Hospice company isn't working out.
If I'm there as the nurse,
I'm an employee of this Hospice company.
Even if I know that we're not serving
this person the best way possible.
I can't recommend that they seek out a
new Hospice team.
But as a doula,
that's going to be the first thing I do
right,
is to get them the care that they need
and deserve.
And so having been on both sides of it,
I don't think that doulas should be
within the system.
I think we need to stay next to it and
working with it and collaborating with it
in order to offer all of the benefits
that we can to a patient and family.
Yeah,
I understand your point of view and and I
largely agree with it.
I just wonder when you're talking about
Medicaid and reimbursement whether at
least some form of licensure beyond the
certification through training would make
it easier to facilitate the payment,
which is an issue here because the equity
fund probably isn't going to cover
everyone's expenses entirely.
And so other sources of funding may very
well be important to ensure the success
of this new program.
Completely agree.
And, and,
and that's part of even why I've gone
back and forth with the idea of does it
make sense for us to seek out that
pathway of reimbursement or do we stay
private pay?
And are we better served to find our own
structures and systems for compensation
and,
and reimbursement like I've done with the
New Mexico Death Care network?
Because that was exactly my thought,
as if if we don't create these systems
and we don't start taking care of
ourselves by nature,
government institutions and bureaucracy
will do so.
And will they then support us in the role
that we're currently in?
Or will our role have to change in order
to fit a system that's already pretty
challenged and in places broken?
So, yeah,
there's there's so much there with all of
that.
I would love to keep talking about that
specifically with you if we could connect
at some point.
All right.
And next we're going to go to Doctor Lita
Fatemi.
She's got her hand up.
And Doctor Fatemi,
your mic should be enabled.
You can unmute when ready.
I'm so excited for this.
It's Doctor Lita Fatemi.
As you can see,
I'm the founder of the Conscious
Physician Psychedelics Academy.
I'm also a Hospice physician with ABQ
Hospice and Palliative Medical Practice.
And I've had the pleasure of getting to
know Daniel over the years and working
together.
And you know, in fact,
I have been a practitioner in the past
who have held space with medicine and a
death doula at the same time,
which was extremely beneficial and
supportive.
And I'm so for this,
I think this is what we need in the care
context of psychedelic care.
And it's greatly appreciated.
And as as you said, Danny,
I love that you're advocating not only
for reimbursement for death doulas,
but really everybody who's involved in
this process.
It's a,
it's a trying process for everyone.
We all need support in all forms,
including the Hospice staff.
Let's say a Hospice company does decide
to participate,
just like with MAID and having a death
doula alongside you is the.
Oh, my gosh, it's quite a game changer.
Thank you so much for what you do and how
you presented this information.
It's beautiful.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Doctor Fatimi.
Let's see.
So also, Danielle, Yeah, if you'd like,
I can also just read through some of
these things in the chat real quick that
people have put in.
So I guess starting with after your talk,
the first one was from Vanessa C.
She just said medicine work is helpful
for the family and community as a whole,
as well as when one is facing EOL.
And then Gregory Evans said the National
End of Life Doula Alliance NEDA
proficiency exam typically costs $115,
plus an additional $50.
00 for NEDA membership,
bringing the total to 165 for the
certification process.
NEDA also partners with training
organizations like Lifespan Doulas where
certification is included in their
training course fees.
And then going down here,
Don Moser says thank you.
I have to leave now but learned a lot.
Let's see.
Lisa Jimenez, thank you, Clifford.
Jen Clemente at the same take away about
spiritual care.
It's not mandated,
but does that risk its non inclusion?
Let's see.
And then Vanessa C again.
Death tool is act as harm reduction
educators,
ceremonialists and peer support.
Death is a psychedelic experience.
We know how to hold this space with or
without fungi medicine.
I've been in serious sorry.
I've been in sessions where the clinician
is present for the dosing and the 1st 15
to 30 minutes in person or virtually.
I held the rest of the sessions as the
doula.
It also removes time restrictions and
then your your husband just being a proud
husband which is great.
Sky Rivers comments,
but without training on psilocybin,
do you then offer this to a patient?
Vanessa C Again,
we are better served to stay independent.
And then finally Gregory Evans again,
in the context of birth doulas,
they are embraced by medical teams
entrusted to identify the proper timing
and triggers to engage with the medical
part of the teams.
They are the advocate and trusted,
trusted to represent the entire community
around the person experiencing the
process of that transition in the context
of universal healthcare and harm
reduction.
I would love to see infrastructure that
supports those roles financially.
All right.
And that's all we had in the chat.
And I don't see any other hands up at
this time with that.
Larry,
I'm gonna defer back to you and see how
you'd like to proceed.
Can I just hop in quick and just comment
quickly on that?
And I'm glancing quickly on.
I don't forget already who said it.
But the that doulas are are already
trained to facilitate the psychedelic
experience of death, right?
And that we do it with or without
medicine.
And I just thank you so much for the way
you said that.
That was perfectly eloquent.
You said it better than I did put in my
experience having having done both,
having participated in medicine
ceremonies,
facilitated medicine spaces and been
present at 17 deathbeds with the the
final breath in the last three years.
It is the same work and I don't think
that there are better positioned support
people in this role than death doulas.
So thank you.
This is Larry.
I'm just trying to share,
do a little bit of a screen share.
Let me see if I can get it to show a
PowerPoint here.
It's not really essential.
Are people hearing me OK?
Yes, we can hear you, Larry.
OK, good.
Sorry,
I'm just trying to unsuccessfully get a
PowerPoint on there.
Danielle, that was amazing.
I mean,
you could see all the the response and
really helpful.
It feels like we're putting like
different pieces of the,
of this together each time,
looking at the spiritual piece,
the looking at the, you know,
looking at the, the, the doula role.
When I look over and I was trying to
share this with people, you know,
when we started the committee,
we had like 7 areas.
I'm going to see if I can actually put
these into the,
into the chat and then take a second to
kind of see where we're at with each of
them.
I think that may be helpful as we're
moving ahead.
So give me a second here.
Yeah.
So everyone see this OK in the chat here.
So these are really the seven things that
we looked at here.
And I'm,
I'm just putting this up for the group to
talk about.
So to see whether we think there's more
information that we need, you know,
first was establishing definition of
scope for end of life criteria.
I think we've gotten a lot of feedback on
that.
A lot of what we've been focusing on here
is the therapeutic team development.
So I think we're getting good information
here.
The inclusion of family and caregivers
we've talked some about.
So I,
I think 1 area that's we haven't had a
lot on here is a sites of end of life
care and I'm hoping some of that will get
covered.
You know when we have talk of, of Hospice,
Jennifer Johnson up in with Red Willow to
cover that area there.
And then the other is development of
psilocybin assisted therapy end of life
care plans that may be helped by James
Brown giving us some information about,
you know, dosing, dosing intervals there.
But I just wanted to kind of open the
discussion to see if people think that
there are other things we want to make
sure that we're covering before we,
you know,
in in the next couple of months or study
comments on any of these.
If not,
y'all get half hour of your life back and
we're all set to to meet next on April
3rd.
OK.
Well, thank you everybody.
We appreciate you all being here.
And again,
thank you to Danielle for the
presentation.
Oh, we do have a hand.
We do have a hand up there.
Yeah.
Erica, I have enabled your microphone.
Please begin when ready.
Are you able to hear me?
Yes.
OK, great.
Yeah, I just wanted to introduce myself.
I'm the lead faculty on A-Team at New
Mexico State University School of Social
Work and Public Health department that
received.
We're going to be part of the faculty
fellows for EU Sona,
U PEP cohort for this 2026.
And so they're helping us to design
curriculum related to psychedelics,
and we're really excited for that and
hope that we could maybe be a hub for
education broadly for all professionals
that are engaged in this,
but specifically for social work.
This is very, yeah, I'm, I'm,
I'm really familiar with the program.
I,
I think it's amazing that you guys have
three people down there and resources.
I've heard they're actually expanding the
that program to include clinicians at
different sites too.
So it seems like a great opportunity to
really to do that.
So I'm just giving my personal excitement
about it.
Yeah.
Just let me know if I can be of support
in any way.
And I look forward to working with all of
you.
If anyone else has any questions,
please raise your hand and I'll be able
to unmute yourself right away.
I believe that concludes it.
I'll pass over back to you, Lawrence.
Just to see if people want to make a note.
So we'll have April 3rd will be a meeting
same time in Friday, April 17th,
same time zone.
And then April 23rd will be the blended
meeting that will be in Albuquerque at
the Bioscience Center.
The address will get listed online.
That'll be from 1:00 to 4:00 and they'll
also be a virtual.
So those are our meetings for the next
for April.
So April is a busy month.
We actually have 33 meetings set up and
the hope is that we'll be in a good
position to start working on more and
developing some recommendations.
Thanks, everybody.
Have a great couple weeks and see
everybody on April 3rd.
Thank you again everybody.
And just so everyone knows,
I did just post all of the next several
meetings into the chat as well if you
want to go and register for those now.
Thank you.
Have a great weekend everyone and thanks
Dominic.
Thank you.